<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: school, | Adventures in code-land]]></title>
  <link href="http://mgsterling11.github.io/blog/categories/school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mgsterling11.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-13T17:52:57-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mgsterling11.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Sterling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Binding Pry, CLI Error Messages, and TDD]]></title>
    <link href="http://mgsterling11.github.io/blog/2015/10/04/binding-pry/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-04T16:59:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mgsterling11.github.io/blog/2015/10/04/binding-pry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I first started considering going the bootcamp route, I began to reach out to friends who are developers to ask about all things programming: did you need a CS degree to get a job?; would anyone hire me?; what kinds of jobs await junior devs who come from bootcamps?; what’s a typical career trajectory in development?; etc. I was nervous about the bootcamp route, too, because it seemed like it could go one of two ways for me: either really well, or very badly. Happily, a good friend of mine is a Flatiron alum and things turned out quite nicely for her, so I decided to take the next step and learn some code.</p>

<p>Now, I needed to prove to myself that I could actually learn to code…</p>

<p>For starters, I completed five or six courses in Codecademy and found myself enjoying programming – a lot. I wanted to take it a step further and write some programs on my own so I could see what it’s like to build one 100% from scratch. I built a few fun little programs, beginning with a banking program that mimics ATMs. It’s a very exciting little program: you can withdraw, deposit, and transfer money between two accounts, and you can also view your balances. Cool, right!? From there, I moved on to Rock Paper Scissors (and then Tic Tac Toe for the Flatiron app). I loved every (sometimes frustrating) minute of building each of these programs. I felt like I was making great progress in a short time, and I enjoyed the new challenge, too.</p>

<p>Of course, in retrospect, I now realize I totally could have been having way more fun when writing these programs (and even while doing the Flatiron prework). I didn’t utilize tests, TDD, or binding pry to help me code. Instead, I was relying purely on the error messages my command line was giving me to see where my programs were breaking. Even during the prework, I somehow missed the memo on how powerful a tool binding pry could be; instead, I figured that the CLI error messages provided pretty much the same kind of feedback: your program is broken, here! And now here! And here, too! (Everywhere, basically.) What I somehow didn’t realize is that you could test your program before the break(s) with binding pry – nor did I realize that binding pry would let you run your code again and again until you got it working, without crashing the program.</p>

<p>After one week at Flatiron, I’m already finding it much easier to remove guesswork from my coding, thanks largely to binding pry (and of course all the learning going on here!). As I write code now, I already have much clearer sense of what’s going on in my program, line by line: what the return values are going to be, what elements in iterators <em>actually</em> correspond to, how deep I actually need to iterate, etc. Binding pry and the command line error message have already helped me to speed up my coding significantly, and I know it’ll only get faster. I’m very excited.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
