<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: interviews | Adventures in code-land]]></title>
  <link href="http://mgsterling11.github.io/blog/categories/interviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mgsterling11.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-13T18:08:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mgsterling11.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Sterling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Approach to interviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://mgsterling11.github.io/blog/2015/11/23/approach-to-interviews/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-23T22:08:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mgsterling11.github.io/blog/2015/11/23/approach-to-interviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re now over two thirds of the way through our Flatiron experience. As we continue to barrel ahead through new material, we&rsquo;re confronting the reality that we&rsquo;ll all be on the job market very(!) soon, and will need to be representing ourselves as professional, ableit beginner, programmers. This can be pretty daunting, for many reasons. Many current developers experience Imposter Syndrome, the classic &ldquo;everyone else is better than me&rdquo; mindset, so it&rsquo;s easy to imagine a bootcamp grad can experience the same misgivings.</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="https://img.washingtonpost.com/rf/image_1484w/2010-2019/WashingtonPost/2012/06/07/CapitalBusiness/Graphics/careercoach11.jpg?uuid=DAAziLDWEeGw96SQqoz3hw">https://img.washingtonpost.com/rf/image_1484w/2010-2019/WashingtonPost/2012/06/07/CapitalBusiness/Graphics/careercoach11.jpg?uuid=DAAziLDWEeGw96SQqoz3hw</a>" width="700" title="&lsquo;" ></p>

<p>As we&rsquo;re heading toward the finish line for the program, I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about the interview process. To better prepare for the techinical compoment,  I&rsquo;ve been working hard to incorporate better habits (i.e. best practices) not only into my code, but the way I approach development, problem solving, and finding a best solution/algorithm.</p>

<p>Gayle Laakmann McDowell, author of CRACKING THE CODING INTERVIEW, offers excellent advice for all parts of the job interview (especially the technical component(s). The book, which has been recommended as a must-read by every developer I&rsquo;ve spoken with, is one I highly recommend everyone takes a read through. Obviously we do have some time before we hit the job market, but she has some guiding principles to approaching the job interviews that I&rsquo;ve found useful in every day programming, too.</p>

<p>When handling anything from simple to highly complicated coding challenges, best steps can include:</p>

<p>1) Listen: When in an interview, listen very carefully to your interviewer. Pay attention to all aspects of the question they mention. Take notes as needed, note any particularities (are you given a hash in an array, an array in a hash, etc.), etc.</p>

<p>2) Example: Whiteboard an example solution, or draw out the problem. Giving yourself visual cues, rather than simply trying to solve the problem entirely in your head, can help a great deal.</p>

<p>3) Brute Force: Just solve the problem, any way you can. Hold off testing edge-cases: just get your solution in working order so that the return will be what you believe it needs to be. Then you can optimize.</p>

<p>4) Optimize: Clean up your solution. Modularize it; condense it; name variables and methods clearly; use helper methods; etc.</p>

<p>5) Walk Through: After you&rsquo;ve cleaned up your solution, go through it with a fine-tooth comb. Is it really clean? Test edge cases. Make sure every method is used; if it&rsquo;s not cut it. If it can be simplified, it means you&rsquo;ve still got refactoring/optimization to do.</p>

<p>6) Implement: Now that you know what direction to head in, and you&rsquo;re certain it&rsquo;s the optimal one, start writing your code.</p>

<p>7) Test: repeat optimize, with your code now actually written out.</p>

<p>What I love most about these guiding principles is that steps 1-5 are all taken before you start coding. These mainly focus on planning and giving your code intent, making sure that your logic is sound, etc. By approaching everyday programming this way, it will be easy to extrapolate these methods and use them during your interview. Interviewers like to see how you react when a problem stumps you: do you panic? Get focused? Talk things out?</p>

<p>Getting these good habits in place before the interview can certainly help make the right impression.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
